Good morning. Today's דף daf is
י"ד. yud-daled. 27th day of the Omer. We yesterday we read the
beginning of what was parts from the top of י"ד עמוד א'.
yud-daled amud-aleph. So the משנה mishna had said had spoken about birds'
nests in trees and that and the it mentioned הקדש hekdesh if
there's a bird's nest לא נהנין ולא מועלין lo nehenin velo moalin
which is the basic idea that if הקדש hekdesh acquires something by
its property there's no מעילה meila because as the רמב"ן Ramban says
it was not had קדושת פה kedushat peh sanctified verbally. And then
the end spoke about if there was a tree in an אשרה
asheira a nest in an אשרה asheira tree a bird's nest in
an עבודה זרה avoda zara tree that was worshipped so then it
says you knock the nest out but you presumably can't climb the
tree because you'll get benefit from the עבודה זרה avoda zara tree
and there's no problem about the nest because there's no concept of
like the property of עבודה זרה avoda zara it's just the status
that this tree was worshipped. So let's take a look now at
the top of י"ד עמוד א'. yud-daled amud-aleph. איתמר עבודת כוכבים שנשתברה
מאליה itmar avodat kochavim shenishtabra me'eileiha if an עבודה זרה avoda zara
broke on its own an idol fell off the table and broke.
רבי יוחנן אמר אסורה Rabbi Yochanan amar asura it remains forbidden. This
is something that was something that was worshipped by as an עבודה
זרה avoda zara by a non-Jew has the status of an idol
and is forbidden in benefit that remains even after it broke as
long as it broke by itself it wasn't it wasn't consciously broken
by one of its worshippers. ריש לקיש אומר
מותרת Reish Lakish omer muteres it's permissible. רבי יוחנן אמר אסורה Rabbi
Yochanan amar asura it's forbidden דלא בטלה עובדי כוכבים delo batla ovdei
kochavim an idol one of its worshippers did not consciously negate its
status by consciously breaking it so therefore its status remains. ריש לקיש
אומר מותרת Reish Lakish omer muteres it's permissible ממילא אמר mimailei amar
because any of its worshippers would naturally say היא גופא לא מצלה
לדידי תצלה hee gufa lo matzla ledidi tatzla it couldn't save itself
you think it's going to save me? So therefore in some objective
way it is בטל batel because any right-thinking person right-thinking idolater would
normally anyway you know could be expected would annul.
Okay so that's this is gonna get into like almost יאוש שלא
מדעת yeush shelo mida'at if you don't know a little.
The question is is that
whether רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is really saying that a particular person
would have or whatever or he's just saying that objective I mean
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish in its objective status is something that is
you know can it be defined objectively without a subjective ביטול bitul
seems to me more what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. איתיביה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן eiseivei
Reish Lakish leRabbi Yochanan so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish asked רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan to try to prove that it is בטל. batel.
הקן שבראש האילן hakan sheberosh ha'ilan
הקן שבראש האילן hakan sheberosh ha'ilan if you have this bird's nest
at the top of a tree and it's של הקדש shel hekdesh
if it's a tree of הקדש hekdesh אין נהנין ואין מועלין. ein
nehenin ve'ein moalin. You can't derive הנאה hana'a rabbinically but there's no
מעילה meila because as we said no קדושת פה. kedushat peh. שבאשרה
sheba'asheira if it's at the top of an אשרה asheira tree יתיז
בקנה yatiz bekana you knock it down with a stick don't climb
the tree but there's no problem you can derive benefit from the
bird's nest. מאי לאו דאיתפר מגופא mai lav de'itpar migufa now where
did it get the twigs for this nest? Presumably we're talking at
least we're not excluding the case that it got the twigs from
the tree itself. So it got the so now you're benefiting from
this nest which is made with twigs
from an אשרה asheira tree.
The nest the nest okay
but the קנה kana used can't be from an אשרה asheira tree
right we're not done about the קנה kana right okay but presumably
but the nest ותני יתיז בקנה ve'tani yatiz bekana so you see
you can knock it down and you can derive benefit. So you
can derive benefit from this nest even though the twigs came from
the אשרה asheira tree. Presumably that's because as soon as the twigs
are broken off even if they're not broken off by human beings
it's considered to be no longer עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So isn't
that a good proof for me says ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish? Says
the גמרא Gemara לא דאייתי עיצי מעלמא lo de'aiti eitzei me'alma not
necessarily we're talking maybe that the twigs came from other trees and
from other places it didn't come from the tree itself.
But if you didn't know that then presumably you couldn't use it
right?
Well that right that would be a question like presumably you'd have
to be concerned that it came from the tree unless there was
some evidence that it came from other trees which is the power
of ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish point that presumably we're not you know
we're including cases where it did could have come from the tree
itself. And the answer is no we know that it only came
from other trees. Okay so now I should tell you that
this
סוגיא sugya is exactly well it's almost exactly paralleled in עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara as you might as you might not be surprised to
hear this question about what happens when an עבודה זרה avoda zara
breaks by itself is primarily a discussion in עבודה זרה Avoda Zara
here it's only being brought in because of the proof that's trying
to be adduced from our משנה. mishna. In עבודה זרה Avoda Zara
this reads a lot smoother. We're about to read a text where
it's like a little bit unclear what they're exactly saying what they're
exactly trying to prove. It's very smoothed over in עבודה זרה Avoda
Zara as would be expected the texts in מעילה Meila sometimes are
not as well edited or you know as as smooth as the
texts in other מסכתות. masechtot. So anyway let's take a look. So
that's what he says. No other types of of of trees. Now
I'm going to read it with the here it's only a slight
emendation that if you look at it sort of points out on
the side and it's the way it reads in עבודה זרה. Avoda
Zara. It says not אי הכי ei hachi which is a challenge
to this but the opposite. דיקא נמי daika nami it also. A
proof to this
is דדמאי של הקדש אין נהנין ואין מועלין d'demai shel hekdesh ein
nehenin v'ein moalin that it says that if it's from, if that
you דדמאי של הקדש אין נהנין ואין מועלין d'demai shel hekdesh ein
nehenin v'ein moalin by the nest that's in the הקדש hekdesh tree.
Now it says, now look at it. If it got, if it
got twigs from other trees, I understand why אין נהנין ואין מועלין.
ein nehenin v'ein moalin. What we've been saying, if הקדש hekdesh just
takes possession of something, so אין נהנין ein nehenin but there's no
מעילה meilah because you didn't verbally sanctify. But if you're trying to
claim ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that it got the twigs from the
tree itself, well, if it got the twigs from the tree itself,
it should be מעילה. meilah. Those are the twigs from the very
tree that was sanctified. So you see, we have to be talking
that it came from other trees because if it's from the tree
itself, א' alef I would say that there's an איסור עבודה זרה
issur avodah zarah by an עבודה זרה avodah zarah tree and ב'
beis there should be an איסור מעילה issur meilah by the case
of הקדש. hekdesh. אלא, Ella, so the גמרא Gemara says no, rather,
you know, no you could answer that by saying בגידולין הבאים לאחר
מכאן b'gidulin habaim l'achar mikan וקסבר אין מעילה בגידולין. v'kasavar ein meilah
b'gidulin. Now,
it could be says what would say ריש לקיש Reish Lakish back,
we're still talking about the tree itself and to me therefore it's
still evidence that there's no problem by עבודה זרה avodah zarah when
it breaks. Why is there no מעילה meilah by the branches of
the tree itself? Because we're talking that those branches grew after you
sanctified it, right? And remember we had this debate, things that grow
after they were sanctified, is there מעילה meilah or not? יש מעילה
בגידולין או אין מעילה בגידולין. yesh meilah b'gidulin o ein meilah b'gidulin.
If הקדש hekdesh just takes possession of something, there's no מעילה. meilah.
Let's say something that's קדוש kadosh grows, גידולין, gidulin, like it bears
fruit or other twigs or other branches, so there there is a
debate. So now we are where are we right now? ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish saying I'm going to assume this is talking that the
twigs came from the tree itself. By עבודה זרה avodah zarah that's
a proof to me that there's no עבודה זרה avodah zarah when
the branches break by itself. By
מעילה, meilah, the way I would explain it is that these are
branches that grew after it was sanctified and therefore there's no מעילה
בגידולין, meilah b'gidulin, but both cases could be talking about
the branches came from the tree itself. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
would say no, the branches came from elsewhere and therefore by עבודה
זרה avodah zarah it would be אסור. assur. By the tree itself,
I don't know what he would say by גידולין, gidulin, but anyway,
certainly if it came from the tree that was there when it
was sanctified it would be it would be מעילה meilah and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it came from a different tree. Okay, so
very simple debate. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says another tree, you can't
prove anything about the status of this tree, and ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says it came from this tree and it shows you that
עבודה זרה avodah zarah when it breaks isn't a problem, and as
far as מעילה meilah we're talking about things that grew later. Yes.
So he would disagree with that other משנה Mishnah because you know
we had the תרנגול tarnigol and its egg, right? And over there...
No, no, no, we already said yesterday that even those positions that
אין מעילה בגידולין ein meilah b'gidulin seem to agree, well, there's there's
the אחרונים Acharonim ask that question because there is a סתם משנה
stam Mishnah that says that there is מעילה meilah by the eggs
and the milk if it's קדשי בדק הבית. kodshei bedek habayis. So
some say that's according to the מן דאמר man d'amar that יש
מעילה בגידולין. yesh meilah b'gidulin. And the other possibility is just say
that that's even more an intrinsic part of the animal of the
thing than things that grow later, like something that comes from within
the body is the milk, the eggs, may be considered more of
the thing itself. But that משנה, Mishnah, so fine you don't like
it, so you say it's the מן דאמר man d'amar that אין
מעילה בגידולין. ein meilah b'gidulin. No, he would say...
יש מעילה בגידולין.
yesh meilah b'gidulin. Right, that's what I'm saying. Anyway,
so now we go on.
Okay, so those are the two ways to read this משנה Mishnah
whether it's the twigs from the tree itself or the twigs from
elsewhere. הגמרא Hagemara now goes on it says הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi
nami mistavra, that also makes sense, now here's where it gets very
complicated, it reads a lot better in עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. הכי
נמי
מסתברא hachi nami mistavra that also makes sense, דאי סלקא דעתך דאייתי
מעלמא, d'ei salka dachtech d'ayisi m'alma, if we're talking that we're talking
about twigs that came from elsewhere, אמאי יתיז
בקנה, amai yatiz b'kaneh, why do you have to knock down the
nest? לשקלינהו בידיה, lishklineihu b'yadeih, just take it directly with your hand.
Now what does one thing have to do with the other, right?
Who cares where the twigs came from? If the reason you're knocking
it down is because we're afraid you're going to let's say derive
benefit if you climb the tree, you support yourself on the tree
or whatever, who cares whether the nest came from here or the
nest came from elsewhere? So anyway in הגמרא עבודה זרה Hagemara Avodah
Zarah there's none of this. תוספות Tosafos explains, it tries to you
know explain that the הוה אמינא hava amina is that the reason
we're telling you to knock it down and not to take it
directly is not we're afraid you're going to derive benefit from the
tree like it's not like you're climbing, presumably it's low enough that
if it says take it directly it means you could reach it.
So if you could reach it and you don't have to climb,
what's the concern? So he says the concern is is that you
might take some of the branches that are part of the tree
itself as you're actually taking the thing. Okay, and if you're taking
it directly as you know and you're manipulating something directly you could
yank things out and you could maybe take some of the branches
itself. If you're doing it with a stick, it's you know you're
not you're not ripping things as much so you're going only going
to most likely get the thing itself. So what he's saying is
look if it came from from you know if it came from
from the tree, I understand why you're afraid that you'll confuse, you'll
rip down some branches with the tree of the tree, you'll confuse
the branches of the tree with the nest and therefore in order
and therefore you'll really get benefit from the tree and therefore in
order not
to...
visually distinct because it comes from different types of wood, okay, that's
what the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* assumes. I know, what can I tell
you? And there- it's a very difficult גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. And this
text in עבודה זרה avodah zarah *Avoda Zara* reads a million times
easier. Anyway, so it says, so if it's from elsewhere, why not
just take it directly? Because then you'll see that there- the stuff
is different and you won't incidentally benefit from the stuff of the
tree. That's at least the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* reads it. So
אמר רבי Rebbe אבא אמר רבי יוחנן לעולם דאתי מעלמא *Amar Rabbi
Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan Le'olam De'asai Me'alma*. No, no, no, we're going
to say it came from elsewhere. ומאי יתיז יתיז אפרוחים *Umai Yatis
Yatis Efrochim*. Now, the לעולם דאתי מעלמא *Le'olam De'asai
Me'alma* actually
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*, it actually
is saying the opposite. Because again, this is רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* has been saying to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*, "I'm going to prove to you that the branches came from
the tree itself." And רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* has been insisting the
branches came from elsewhere. So in עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*, אמר רבי
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan* is saying
"I'm willing to concede the branches came from the tree itself, and
I'm still going to be able to explain it." So it's the
exact opposite of לעולם דאתי מעלמא *Le'olam De'asai Me'alma*, so I'm going
to read it without those three words. And the ב״ח *Bach* crosses
out those three words, okay, again trying to make it work better
with the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*. But let's
try to get some פשט *Pshat* that makes sense here. So until
now, what has been the debate? רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says the
branches came from elsewhere. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says- mean the nest.
The wood came from elsewhere, ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says it came
from the tree itself. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says, "Because I say
it came from the tree itself, I have proof that עבודה זרה
*Avoda Zara* that breaks is מותר muttar, *Mutar*. As far as מעילה
meilah *Me'ila*, it's because it's stuff that grew later, after you were
הקדיש *Hikdish* it." רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says, "No, no, the only-
it all came from elsewhere." Okay, and then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
had some question, like it thought that that was hard to explain
why you would have to poke it down if it came from
elsewhere. Fine. Now רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, רבי אבא *Rabbi Abba* in
the name of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, is going to say "I
can even agree to you ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* that it came
from the- it came from the tree itself." If it came from
the tree itself, how can you get benefit from the nest? How
can you derive- right? I mean the nest is made out of
forbidden wood. So what are you getting benefit from? Who says when
I say knock down the nest, what do you think you're actually
interested in? The birds, right? Says who says you're getting benefit from
the wood, right? Fine, the wood is אסור assur, *Asur*, עבודה זרה
*Avoda Zara*, it's מעילה meilah *Me'ila*, whatever. That's not the point.
So then why need a stick for that? Why not just go
and take the bird?
Because you're afraid that if you go and you grab it or
whatever, maybe you'll- same type of idea, incidentally you'll take from the
wood or back to the idea that you might climb the tree.
Let's read the inside, let's read the inside. Fine. אמר רבי אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Abba Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, so take out
the next three words, not לעולם דאתי מעלמא *Le'olam De'asai Me'alma*. He
actually says "I'll concede that it's from the tree itself." ומאי יתיז
*Umai Yatis*? What does it mean poke it down? יתיז אפרוחים *Yatis
Efrochim*. Poke it down so that the chicks fall out or fly
out and benefit from the chicks. So yeah, it's- if it were
the wood itself, it'd be a מעילה meilah *Me'ila* problem, there'd be
an עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara* problem. The whole thing here is- the
whole thing here is about the chicks. Now and now we clarify
it. אמר ליה רבי יעקב לרבי ירמיה *Amar Lei Rabbi Yaakov LeRabbi
Yirmiyah*, אפרוחים כאן וכאן מותרים *Efrochim kan ve-kan mutarim*. If it comes
to the chicks themselves, then whether it's the עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*
case or the מעילה meilah *Me'ila* case, the chicks are okay because
we wouldn't say, for example, by the chicks we wouldn't say לא
נהנין ולא מועלין *Lo Nehenin Velo Moalin*. Why? Because you know, this
gets into interesting- well yeah, but why don't we say the tree
is קונה koneh *Koneh*, for example? So this gets to a whole
question about to what degree if your- can you be קונה *Koneh*
birds that fly from elsewhere? You know, fundamentally they're free, they're not
constrained, you don't have any control over them and so on. Okay,
so he's saying even by הקדש hekdesh, *Hekdesh*, where it's about ownership
normally matter, the birds are always going to be okay. ביצים כאן
וכאן אסורים *Beitzim kan ve-kan asurim*. The eggs are אסור assur *Asur*.
By מעילה meilah. *Me'ila* it's not hard to understand why, because there's
a sense of
the tree- a sense of קנין רשויות *Kinyan Reshuyot*, the tree owns
it, but even by
עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*, the idea is that you know, the same
way according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, the nest is אסור assur.
*Asur* because it comes from the wood of עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara*,
things that are very connected to the nest, rabbinically will be an
extension of that. So the same way the nest is אסור *Asur*,
we would אסור *Asur* the eggs. אמר רב אשי *Amar Rav Ashi*,
רב אשי *Rav Ashi* qualifies: אם אפרוחים צריכין לאימן כביצים דמו *Im
efrochim tzrichin le'iman kebeitzim damu*. If they're chicks that still need their
mother, so basically they're tied to the nest, so if they're tied
to the nest, then they're like the eggs and they're part of
the nest. So now we have a very simple alternate explanation. Okay,
is this nest
אסור *Asur* or not? So- so a simple read of the משנה
Mishnah. *Mishna*, it's not. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says "That's evidence to
me that it came from the tree- I assume it came from
the tree itself, evidence that עבודה זרה *Avoda Zara* that breaks is
מותר *Mutar*. And as far as מעילה meilah *Me'ila*, it's- it's something
that grew later." רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* has two answers: either the
nest came from elsewhere, number one, and that's why there's none of
those problems, or, no... Or no, fine, the physical nest is אסור,
okay, for the reasons because it is עבודה זרה and it's not
גידולי הבאים לאחריה. gidulei habaim l'achareita. The eggs, the chicks are מותר,
okay, and that's when we're talking about knocking them down, we're talking
about knocking down the chicks. Maybe we'd also אסור, we'd also answer
the eggs and the chicks that need their mother, they're considered connected
to the nest, not that they're דאורייתא d'oraisa problem, but דרבנן derabbanan
at least, they're similar to the nest itself. But I say the
nest and the things connected are אסור and we're only talking about
the chicks. Very nice, two different reads of the משנה. Mishnah. Okay,
now we go on to the next משנה. Mishnah הגזברין שלקחו עצים,
HaGizbarin shelakechu eitzim, now this is very interesting because it starts talking
about the process of when do people when they donate things to
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, when do they sanctify it. So the
הגזברין, HaGizbarin, the treasurers that purchased wood, מועלין בעצים moalin ba'eitzim ואין
מועלין לא בשיפויה ולא בנביה. v'ein moalin lo b'shipuya v'lo b'nivya. You,
there's מעילה me'ilah. by the wood but there is not מעילה me'ilah.
by the like
sawdust and the נביה nivya which is like the you know leaves
or whatever, right, that you cut off of the wood in order
to make beams out of it. Now notice that that's different than
the previous משנה Mishnah, that says the last line which typically should
have been connected to this one which says that if you sanctify
a forest, המקדיש את החורש, hamakdish es hachoresh, מועלין בכולו, moalin b'chulo,
all parts of the forest are אסור. Now what's the difference? Presumably
the difference is again, this is like a קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf,
קדושת דמים kedushas damim type of a thing. If I'm buy if
you donated your forest to הקדש, hekdesh okay, that's you know, it'll
sell the forest and make a lot of money out of it.
It's not going to directly put that forest into the you know,
into the temple structure. Might use some parts of it, but obviously
its value far exceeds the just the use of some of the
wood and that's something that therefore it all belongs to הקדש hekdesh,
business and there's there's
מעילה me'ilah? by all of them. If the גזבר gizbar buys a
a if he buys a
log, like that would be a good way of saying it, he
buys a log, okay, its purpose is he's going to make out
of it beams in order to build into the temple, in order
to build into the walls or wherever those beams are needed.
Oh, we're not talking about the עצים eitzim on the מזבח? mizbeach?
No,
presume no, I don't think so at all. But anyway, because it's
all about גזבר, gizbar, when we talk about גזבר, gizbar, you're talking
about like like structure and the treasury and not whatever. Okay, so
therefore that type of a thing, anything that is, it's sort of
like in that case, you know what's the difference, it's the difference
between the eggs and the milk of of the things you sanctify.
Eggs and milk of a קרבן korban are not the עיקר ikkar
part of the קרבן, korban, so therefore that's more about קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf and there's no מעילה me'ilah? by the eggs and the
milk. Whereas eggs and milk about something that's just owned by הקדש,
hekdesh, like a chicken, right, or whatever, a donkey, that is about
value and that there is מעילה. me'ilah. So the same here. If
it's about a forest, then that's sort of like the chicken and
the donkey. It's all about ownership and every little thing counts. If
it's about building it into the temple wall, that's like the eggs
and milk, then the then the what do you call it, the
sawdust is like the eggs and the milk of a קרבן. korban.
It's not really relevant to this as a beam. This is about
being a beam and being built in. It's more קדושת הגוף kedushas
haguf and therefore there's no מעילה me'ilah? by that. Yes.
So back in the in the time when we had a temple,
the shavings and so forth were basically useless. Right. Now a sawmill
will take them and turn them into wood products that are that
they make a lot of money for.
Right. So again, if you if if
I think that's a good,
you see, the tricky thing is, yeah, it's a good question.
You know, like why does this whole sense here of קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf have to start right away? Meaning if I take this
animal and I say הרי זה עולה, harei zeh olah, it's clearly
about קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf and the eggs or milk actually wouldn't
work by an עולה, olah, חטאת, chattas, whatever, are not part of
its identity of an עולה. olah. If the גזבר gizbar comes along
and he buys twenty logs and he is going to go and
he is going to make beams out of it and build it
in הקדש, hekdesh, but he's got this big factory and he knows
that a byproduct of this will be a lot of sawdust that
he can sell. Why should we assume that that initial purchase is
a קדושת הגוף? kedushas haguf? Why shouldn't that initial purchase be about
a קדושת דמים? kedushas damim? And when you finally have the log
that's ready not the log, the beam that's ready to be built
in, that will be a קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf and the other
stuff remains a קדושת דמים. kedushas damim. Yeah, it's a very good
question. I don't really know. You see, it's very tricky when you
talk about קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf of not קרבנות korbanos but things
that are built into the temple. Because it's so fungible there, what
are you going to use directly, what are you not going to
use directly? And you could start with something and then change your
mind and say, 'Hey, I'll make more money if I sell this.'
So exactly that issue is a very tricky one and it's a
very good question.
So, yeah, it's also it's not it's not, you know, an animal,
a sentient being, and you can קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf really applies
to an animal and it's a borrowed term when it comes to,
you know,
right, I mean you can have you have קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf
by like a מנחה, minchah,
you know, there, right, once you put it but in the כלי,
kli, you know,
it's like a borrowed term you know, that's interesting,
interesting.
So it is a good question here, you know, but exactly that
distinction and when you deal with the difference between קדושת דמים Kedushat
Damim and קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf by בדק הבית. Bedek Habayit. So
we're not saying it just be the sawdust,
everything but the actual beam itself. Presumably, right. Including like the bark
and whatever it is. Presumably, yes. Okay, okay. Now let's take a
look at the גמרא.
Gemara I mean if you look
at the מפרשים Mefarshim here, right, the last
line of the משנה, Mishnah. he says, והני היינו עלין שלהן לפי
שגזברים לא קנו והקדישו אלא דבר שצריך לבנין ולא שיפוי וניבייא. V'hanei
hainu alin shelahen lefi shegizbarin lo kanu vehikdishu ela davar shetzarich lebinyan
velo shipui venivya. And it's like when they purchased it, their intent
to sanctify was only the part that was actually going to be
the beam. It's like what does Michelangelo say, right, but I cut
away all the parts that weren't David? Right. So they've always sanctified,
you know, all the other. I'm מקדיש makdish only the beams that
are within this. But let's say he didn't. Let's say as you
said, he knew that you could make a lot of money by
the sawdust as well. Maybe he was קונה all of it and
the beam itself was קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf and the other part
was קדושת דמים. Kedushat Damim. It's a very good question. Let's take
a look now at the גמרא. Gemara אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, בונים
בחול ואחר כך מקדישין. Bonin bechol ve-achar kach makdishin. You build with
non-sanctified items and then you sanctify them. Now that's interesting. You only
sanctify after everything's already built. There's an obvious reason for this. You
don't want people to do מעילה. me'ilah Right, you don't want to
accidentally do מעילה. me'ilah.
So that's the גמרא Gemara is going to say at the end.
But let's first see how it explains. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? מאן
דמסתנדב מעות, Man de-misnadeiv ma'ot, if somebody donates money, מקדש להו, makdish
lehu, דאמר תחול קדושת מעות אבניין, de-amar techol kedushat ma'ot abinyan, ויהיב
להו לאומנין בשכרן. ve-yahiv lehu le-umanin bischaran. So somebody that donates money
sanctifies it and if you look at the side they stick in
the word לפיכך lefichach and therefore you have to say let the
sanctity of the money go on the structure and give the money
to the workers in their fee. What? How did that explain it?
So here's what תוספות Tosafos says it means. It means the following.
As you know, you cannot transfer
קדושה. kedusha. If I sanctify a hundred dollars, here's my hundred דרכמה
drachma to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay. Now, let's say you
are my workers and you built this whole thing and now I
have to pay you a hundred דרכמה. drachma. Here's the hundred דרכמה.
drachma. Only problem, I'm giving you money with קדושה. kedusha. How do
you get the קדושה kedusha off that money so that you can
benefit from it? So you transfer it to the בניין? binyan?
So
well that's where we're going. So if I just try to do
that straight, it would be a problem. But if we did this,
if we basically said
build, you take the raw materials. I'm going to pay you for
everything, the raw materials and your work or whatever. Or maybe I
buy the raw materials separately, doesn't matter. You go ahead and you
take
all this wood that started out being worth, I don't know, ten
דרכמה. drachma. And you go ahead and because of all of your
work and all of your construction, it's now worth fifty דרכמה. drachma.
So presumably there's an assumption here that your pay is equal to
the degree to which this stuff has improved now. Okay. I just
got through some home improvements and anybody knows that you can spend
like $20,000 or $50,000 on a kitchen but your actual property value
only goes up a small portion of that. Anyway, there's an assumption
here, we'll actually have a different scenario in a minute, that your
fee is equal to the improvement of that this thing has improved.
So if I were to pay you upfront, where's the קדושה kedusha
going? But if I wait till everything is built and then I
pay you, so then the קדושה kedusha transfers to that fifty now
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash has improved fifty דרכמה drachma and that's
sort of represented by this new wall here or this new engraving
or whatever. That has not been sanctified yet, so I'm now going
to sanctify that and by transferring the money off the קדושה kedusha
off this money and I'm going to give you the money. So
that's why we want to do it this way in order that
we have a way of transferring the קדושה kedusha from the money.
So let's read that again.
So what does בונים בחול bonin bechol mean?
Meaning that you,
the workers, build with non-sanctified items. Okay. Because the same thing that's
true about paying the workers, by the way, is also true about
paying the person for, well actually no, that's easier. Meaning if you're
selling me the wood, right, then that's easier. I could give you
the money for the wood and the קדושה kedusha could transfer to
the wood. Okay. So this really doesn't explain so much why the
material has to be חול. chol. We're going to get to that
later. Right, it explains more why the workers and whatever why that
I have to wait till they're done to do it. It's probably
also easier to do why the material has to be חול chol
for the following reason. The same way I can't transfer the קדושה
kedusha to the abstract labor, it's an interesting question. If this wood
was already sanctified and you improved its value, the physical object, let's
say you made engravings on this wood, right, or you built it
into, the physical object was always קדוש. kadosh. So where am I
transferring the קדושה kedusha to? Abstract improvement of the object? So we
want something physical and concrete to transfer the קדושה kedusha to. So
if the actual wood or stones are not קדוש kadosh and now
you've increased it, so now I've got a stone worth 50 drachma,
but I actually have a stone that's not קדוש, kadosh, now I'm
going to be able to transfer the קדושה kedusha from the money
to the stone. But if the stone started off as קדוש, kadosh,
that'd be a lot more, you know, nebulous. What am I exactly
transferring it to? The same way I'm transferring it to the abstract
work that they did. Okay, so that's why we wanted it all
to be חול chol and then to be improved and then the
קדושה kedusha is transferred and then I can pay the workers. So
let's read that again in the משנה.
Mishnah's What? This is not our משנה's Mishnah's case? Because our משנה's
Mishnah. case was... We'll get to our משנה.
mishna. בונין בחול ואחר כך מקדישין. Bonin bechol ve'achar kach makdishin. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? Why? מאן דמשתדיב זוזי מקדיש להו. Man demishtadeiv zuzei
makdish lehu.
So somebody who gives, who promises money to the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash will normally sanctify the money and hand it over. ואנו בעי
למיתב אגרא לאומני. Va'anu bei lemeisav agra le'umnei. לפיכך צריך שיאמר Lefikach
tzarich sheyomar
and therefore we have to say, we being the גזבר gizbar or
whatever, תיחול קדושת מעות אבניין, Teichol kedushas ma'os abinyan,
let the קדושה kedusha of the money go on the structure, ויהבו
לאומני בשכרן Veyahavu le'umnei besacharan and then I can give the money
and pay the workers. Okay, so we want there to be something
concrete that is not sanctified, that is improved, and then I'll be
able to transfer the קדושה kedusha from the money off of it.
Now, מיתבי, meisivei, let's take a look about this. דף י"ד עמוד
ב'. Daf yud dalid amud beis. מותר הקטורת מה היו עושים בה?
Mosar haktoret mah hayu osim bah? What would they do with the
leftover קטורת? ktoret? They would make קטורת ktoret 365 מנה maneh per
year corresponding to the days of the calendar year, plus a
three extra for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. The problem is is that as we know, we have a
lunar calendar. So and you have to use, you can only do
קרבנות ציבור korbanos tzibur from the new communal funds that are collected,
you know, every, you start collecting it אדר, Adar, you have
them available at ניסן Nisan and you have to buy it from
the new funds. So the, so now if you didn't have to
buy it from the new funds, it would be great. We have
365 מנה maneh every, the normal years, there's a little bit left
over, 11 left over, you start collecting them, and then when you
have a leap year, you'll have enough of this קטורת ktoret in
order to use. That would be perfect if it were not for
the problem that you have to buy it from the new communal
funds. So what are you going to do? So what you have
to basically do is arrange so that you can desanctify, sort of
like museums, what do they do when they sell, it's called deaccessioning?
No, when museums sell art, not decommission, was that it?
No, there's another word I think, deaccessioned or something.
Anyway, it's like a fancy word for selling it. But they don't
want to seem like we actually sold this Van Gogh, we just
deaccessioned it or something. Anyway, anyway, maybe you're right, maybe it is
decommission. Anyway, okay, so what we have to do is we have
to desanctify the קטורת, ktoret, and then buy it back with the
new communal funds so that if this year winds up and that
to be, we can use it this year, and then it will
still work. It's like the carryover days, you know, you get like
your sick leave or whatever so that when we finally need it,
it will be purchased with the new communal funds and we'll be
able to use it. So how do we do this each year?
Sort of desanctifying it and repurchasing it with the new communal funds?
So here's how you would do it. מותר הקטורת מה היו עושים
בה? Mosar haktoret mah hayu osim bah? How would, what would you
do with it? היו מפרישין הימנה שכר האומנין, Hayu mafrishin himenah sechar
ha'umnin, so you would separate out, I'm missing perhaps the word הימנה,
himenah, but you would separate out money that you had to pay
for workers. סתם, Stam, because that's where you have most of your
money, is money that you're going to be paying for materials and
for workers, you know, that's, so you separate out money that you
would pay for workers ומחללין אותה על מעות האומנין. umachalelin osah al
ma'os ha'umnin. So now, assuming that this money is not הקדש, hekdesh
the money that you would pay the workers, you transfer the קדושה
kedusha of the קטורת ktoret to the money to the worker's money.
Again, not that you've paid them yet, you haven't paid them, the
money you have for the workers. Okay, now the קטורת ktoret is
not sanctified. ונותנין אותה לאומנין, Venosnin osah le'umnin, and then you say
to the workers, hey guess what, this month you're not being paid
with cash, you're being paid with קטורת. ktoret. Okay, and you give
them the קטורת. ktoret. But don't get too upset because וחוזרים ונוטלים
אותה מתרומה חדשה, vechozrim venotlin osah mitrumah chadashah, you repurchase it from
them with the money, with the new funds. Okay, so you say
oh, you have קטורת? ktoret? Would you like to sell us some
קטורת? ktoret? Here's the new funds, and you purchase it. So now
you've purchased קטורת ktoret with the new funds. Okay, so but now
we've got a problem. Wait a second, can I just explain that
one more time what happened? So here's my קטורת ktoret that has
קדושה, kedusha, right, it has the old קדושה. kedusha. I can't use
it as a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, meaning I can use it
presumably and this is interesting, presumably I can use it for בדק
הבית bedek habayis purposes but I can't use it as a קרבן
ציבור, korban tzibur, that has to be built with with new funds.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to say here,
this is green to represent cash, okay, so I'm going to go
ahead and I transfer this קדושה kedusha onto this cash. Okay, then
I go ahead and I say here, I'm paying you with קטורת.
ktoret. Okay, now, oh, you don't have any use for קטורת? ktoret?
No, no, no, not this, this is old קדושה... kedusha... And now
I'll purchase this
and now this has the קדושה kedusha of this year's money
of תרומה חדשה truma chadasha and I can use this for קרבן
ציבור. korban tzibor. And now I'm left with this cash. So fine,
I'll do with it what I do with normal money that has
קדושה. kedusha. I'll find some other way, you know, next time I
build something in the wall, I'll transfer the קדושה kedusha there and
I'll pay the... because the fact that it's last year's קדושה kedusha
is only relevant for קרבן ציבור korban tzibors that are brought this
year, right? It's not relevant for other things. Now I would say
it's quite fascinating that you can have קטורת, ketores, something that has
קדושת קטורת, kedushas ketores, which is something that it's not yet a
fully actualized קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf because it hasn't yet, you know,
been put in a כלי שרת, kli shareis, but that that can
effectively be redirected to something that's going to be, you know, used
in the בנין binyan of the מקדש. Mikdash. So again, how some
of these categories, you know, the exact rigidity between the categories is
sometimes a bit of a question. Okay, but there's still a prohibition
that the person having קטורת, ketores, like he can't make... Oh, you
can't make it, right, you can own it. Right, and you can...
and you could have הנאה... hana'ah... Well right now it doesn't have
any קדושה. kedusha. Uh-huh. So for the time being, yes. So if
I wanted to keep קטורת ketores I could, is that it? Presumably,
yes. Is there a formal way that you transfer the קדושה kedusha
from the קטורת ketores to the money? So right, so, you know,
it's just it's in the back of my סידור siddur for... Right,
so it's basically that type of a thing, you know, הרי זה
מחולל על זה, harei zeh mechulal al zeh, I mean the גמרא
Gemara by תמורה Temurah used different languages because one, you know, but
קדושה... kedu... you should say קדושה זו תחול על זה, kedusha zu
tachol al zeh, something like you basically say, yeah, let the קדושה
kedusha of this be removed and go on to that. Now of
course, okay, but I thought what you were going to say, which
תוספות Tosafos asks, which is: I don't get it. If you can
take the קדושה kedusha here and put it on the old money,
then just why do I have to pay the workers? Just take
the קדושה kedusha from the new money and put it on this!
But he says, you know, it's like it should look בדרך הטבע.
b'derech hateva. There's that joke, you know, the joke about the... you
know, my רבי is so great, whatever, he can stand on a
bench and look for three miles, just why does he have to
stand on a bench? Because it needs to be בדרך הטבע. b'derech
hateva. So anyway, so... so תוספות Tosafos says, you know, we'd rather
do it as a type of a transaction. It doesn't look as
if the whole thing is a game.
At least there's a point where we actually have to buy it
from the new money. It really makes it much more look like
we
are actually buying, you know, buying new קטורת ketores using new money
to do something
as opposed to it all being a game.
Anyway, that's the basic case. Okay, so now what's the question? בכל
זאת נוטלין סמי מתרומה חדשה. bechol zos notlin samei mitrumah chadasha.
So the גמרא Gemara says: אמאי? Amai? ליהוי בנין! Leihei binyan! Why
did you have to transfer
it onto their money, right, the money
that you're going to give to the workers? If you say that
the structure over there has now improved and you haven't yet
paid the workers for it and you're going to transfer קדושה kedusha
from the money to, you know, to the structure, so why
not just take the קדושה kedusha of this
קטורת ketores and transfer it straight there and save yourself all this
rigamarole with the other money? The גמרא Gemara says: דליכא בנין. D'leika
binyan. Okay, there's nothing recently that's been built that we can transfer
the קדושה kedusha to. והא אמסו ונקתני? Veha amsu u'nektani? What do
you mean? You got workers you paid! זה... Zeh... Oh, but it
means workers of בנין. binyan. Maybe, that's interesting. But then it would
be אומנין, umnim, אומנין umnim is more like craftsmen, you know, it's
not like the, right, it's not בנין binyan workers. So the גמרא
Gemara says: דליכא בנין כשיעור מוס. D'leika binyan keshurmos. Ah, but the
improvements aren't equivalent to what you owe the אומנין. umnim. Now that's
what תוספות Tosafos says, I don't get it, so why are you
paying people so... so that's why I was thinking about my kitchen.
Because not my kitchen, my bathroom. Because very often you can actually
have to pay the money you pay for an improvement is not
equal is more than the actual capital improvement of the thing itself.
You still need the work done, okay? So but it doesn't necessarily
mean that it equals the capital improvement. So basically it says okay
because the capital improvement there is only a hundred, my קטורת ketores
is worth two hundred, I owe two hundred to my אומנין, umnim,
so the way I'm going to do it is I'm going to
do it through, you know, the money I owe the אומנין, umnim,
I'm not going to do it through the בנין, binyan, there's not
enough. So the גמרא Gemara says: והאמר שמואל הקדש שוה מנה שחיללו
על שוה פרוטה מחולל. Veha'amar Shmuel, hekdesh shaveh maneh shechilelo al shaveh
perutah mechulal. What a minute? Who cares? שמואל Shmuel says that if
you transfer קדושה kedusha even of a hundred מנה maneh to a
פרוטה, perutah, it works even if it's disproportionate to the value. So
why can't you just transfer the קטורת ketores to the בנין binyan
if you say that you're בונה בחול? boneh bechol? So the גמרא
Gemara says: הני מילי דיעבד דעבד לכתחילה לא. Hani mili dievad, de'avad.
Lechatchila lo. That would be דיעבד dievad if you did it, it
works. You're not supposed to. Even though, and תוספות points this out,
normally the reason you're not supposed to is because הקדש hekdesh loses
out in the bargain obviously if you do a disproportionate transfer. Here
הקדש hekdesh isn't losing anything out, הקדש hekdesh. is doing the whole
situation to begin with, but nevertheless the rules are we don't like
fooling around, we don't like transferring things of different values even if
in this given case there would be no loss to הקדש. Hekdesh,
Okay, so that's one reason, because it allows us to transfer the
קדושה kedusha to something concrete, right? רב פפא Rav Pappa says an
easier reason. רב פפא אמר היינו טעמא. Rav Pappa amar hayinu ta'ama.
היינו טעמא דבונים בחול. Hainu taama de-bonin be-chol. Here's the reason that
you wait to to be מקדיש makdish the objects: דלא ניתנה תורה
למלאכי השרת, de-lo nittena Torah le-mal'achei ha-shareit, because the Torah wasn't given
to angels, right, we're human beings and we have to try to
work with that. So, אמרי דילמא בעי למיגזא וזדלייהו amri dilma ba'ei
le-migza ve-zadla'ihun and they're going to sit on the, you know, they'll
sit on the stones, they'll sit on some of the material they're
supposed to be building with. אי בנא בקודשא I bana be-kudsha and
if you were the stones had been sanctified, אשתכח דקא מעיל בקודשא,
ishtakach de-ka ma'al be-kudsha, that you are you are being now מועל
mo'el in הקדש, so very simple explanation. Now of course the difference
is that this emphasizes that the raw materials are not sanctified, as
opposed to the other thing which is more focused on the work
that the workers did. So according to this maybe he would say
you could pay the workers' weight with קדושה Kedusha funds and maybe
it does transfer to the abstract, you know, work that they've done.
It's not clear how he, what his position is in terms of
the payment of the workers, where does the קדושה Kedusha go? His
empha- maybe so it maybe he would agree that it's also true,
but the other approach that it transfers to the physical improvements, but
anyway here he says his emphasis is the the materials they can't
be קודש kodesh because you might incidentally be מועל. mo'el. So now
we're going to ask from our משנה. mishna תנן: Tnan: הגזבר שלקח
את העצים מועלין בהן ואין מועלין לא בשיפוי ולא בנביה. hagizbar she-lakach
et ha-eitzim mo'alin ba-hen ve-ein mo'alin lo be-shipuy ve-lo be-neviyah. If the
גזבר gizbar purchased beams or whatever wood, logs, you're מועל mo'el with
them, but not with the sawdust. ואמאי מועלין בהן? Ve-amai mo'alin ba-hen?
Why is there מעילה? me'ilah You said you're going to wait to
be מקדיש makdish it. And again notice that the גמרא Gemara asks
this only on the second explanation. Because the first explanation maybe could
have limited itself completely to what to to paying the workers. This
explanation completely focuses on the raw materials. So because in this explanation
where it's all about the raw materials, the משנה is a clear
cut is a clear problem. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמאי מועלין
בהן, ve-amai mo'alin ba-hen, why is there מעילה? meilah. הכא נמי להוי
בחול, Hacha nami lehava be-chol, דאמרי דילמא בעי למיגזא וזדלייהו ואשתכח דקא
מעל בקדשים. de-amri dilma ba'ei le-migza ve-zadla'ihun ve-ishtachach de-ka ma'al be-kodshim. So
say the same thing, he should have bought this beam, he should
have bought it and not sanctified it in order that you should
not inadvertently sit on it and do מעילה. meilah, So אמר רב
פפא, amar Rav Pappa, אי בעצים דמכאן ואילך הכא נמי. i be-eitzim
di-mikan va-eilech hacha nami. You know, if if he had to buy
if he had to buy wood for future construction, construction jobs, you're
right, he wouldn't have sanctified it the גזבר. gizbar. אלא כי תנן
במתניתין בעצים דיומי. Ella ki tnan be-matnisin be-eitzim de-yomei. We're talking that
right now he needs a beam for today. Okay, and right now
they need a beam to put right into the structure right now.
So if it's only if it's to be used immediately, he's not
concerned that it's going to be sitting around, right? In a construction
site you have a lot of raw material lying around, that we're
concerned about, something used for the day we're not concerned about. But
you could say why not play it safe? Yeah I know it's
a good question. If someone were to walk over to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and sit down on the stones, is that not
מעילה? meilah Well it's part of the structure. Well he's outside, he's
not allowed to sit, was it in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
he's not allowed to sit? Well he he means like leans against
a wall, you lean against a wall. Or you're standing on it.
Or you lean against the wall. Wasn't there מעילה before it's installed?
Right. I mean there is גמרות Gemaras that talk about what do
you call it, about like getting being נהנה neheneh from the shade
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and there's a whole question about
you know about that being an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah and איסור
מעילה. issur me'ilah. So why is why would the shade be any
different than leaning against the wall? I understand that because how can
you you know if you're in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash how
can you not be in the shade? You can't definitely only walk
in the sunny parts and things like that. Right, right, that's a
really good question. I mean unless you can talk about the fact
that they were only מקדיש makdish it, that's it kind of part
of the way. Right exactly, that somehow they were מקדיש makdish it
of the nature of the קדושה kedusha was you know exactly to
allow them to be available for that type of הנאה, hana'ah, but
then you wonder why the גמרא Gemara. didn't say that? I'll have
to check the גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim for the גמרא has
that whole discussion by the shade from the wall. So why I
think it actually says we don't have a פסחים Pesachim here. I
think it actually does distinguish between whether it's תוכו עשוי tocho asuy
and but no that's I'll have to double check that, but that's
a very good question. It might be that the answer has to
do with like this at how it was stipulated, but and but
it's not stipulated to be used for the workers to sit on
it. But again okay. So הדרן עלך ולא חטאת. Hadran alach v-lo
chatas. So that was the end of that פרק. perek. Maybe we'll
just end here doing a little time. I did want to say,
even keep on trying to get ahead, I did want to say
because it came up the other day, the question about the wool
of a קרבן, korban, right? What's the story about that we talked
about the eggs and the milk and so on. So there is
first of all a גמרא in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah that speaks
about the horns of an עולה, olah, that there are horns of
a שלמים shelamim and it speaks that there is מעילה. It talks
about using it for a שופר shofar and it has questions about
מצוות לאו ליהנות ניתנו mitzvos lav leihanot nitnu and all those issues,
but anyway it's clear that מעילה is relevant. the horns. Okay, now
the horns is obviously on the one hand it grows, but on
the other hand it's like sort of like a permanent part of
the animal and so on. As far as the, as far as
the wool is concerned, there is also a גמרא in פסחים Pesachim
on ל"ג עמוד א' lamed gimmel amud aleph that speaks about that
somebody that is מתחמם בגיזי עולה, mischamem b'gizei olah, warms himself with
the shearings from an עולה, olah, is מועל. moel. So makes it
clear that there is מעילה. I guess my question would be, you
know, would that apply to, again, would we have the types of
discussions like you do in הבא לאחר מכאן? habai le-achar mikan? Let's
say I sanctified it and then I sheared it and then there
was new wool that grew. Would that be also מעילה, or are
we just talking about the wool that was on it at the
moment that I sanctified it? Because the real comparison to the milk
and the eggs is what happens when it grows later. So it's,
you can't prove that from that גמרא. That could have been wool
that was on it when I sanctified it. So I really still
don't know about it, but it is, there is a גמרא about
horns and about wool that there is מעילה by both of them,
so now you know.